{"tossups": [{"question": "In this letter, the writer claims that, \u201cIt is essential that public opinion should be enlightened\u201d in a section on the education of the masses. The writer of this letter claims that the \u201calternate domination of one faction over another is itself a frightful despotism.\u201d In this letter, the writer states that, \u201cThe shade of retirement is as necessary to me as it will be welcome.\u201d Written and published in September, 1796, for ten points, name this final presidential statement written by the owner of Mount Vernon.", "answer": "George<em><b> Washington</b></em>\u2019s<em><b> Farewell Address</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This organization lost nearly 10,000 men at an engagement at Raate Road where it was defeated by Hjalmar Siilasvuo. While head of this organization, Mikhail Frunze defeated Baron Wrangel during a civil war. Georgy Zhukov once commanded this organization whose flag shows an unfilled yellow star against the backdrop of its namesake color. For ten points, name this armed force that was created after the 1917 Russian Revolution and that opposed the White Army.", "answer": "Workers\u2019 and Peasants\u2019<em><b> Red Army</b></em> (prompt on descriptions of the Soviet/Russian army)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Keith Quincy controversially claimed that this ethnic group had an independent kingdom from 400-900 AD. The Spirit Catches You and You Fall Down by Anne Fadiman tells of the struggles of an immigrant family from this ethnic group living in Merced, California, a community with some 5000 of these people. A subgroup of the Miao, the CIA recruited thousands of these people to fight in the Indochina Wars. For ten points, name this often persecuted ethnic minority from China and southeast Asia.", "answer": "<em><b> Hmong</b></em> (accept<em><b> Hmoob</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was shot during a 1977 siege during which Hanafi Muslims took 149 hostages at the District Building. This man served as the first chairman of SNCC [SNICK] and protested the 1972 blaxploitation film Super Fly by forming a group called BANG. This man succeeded Walter Washington in his most prominent position and won a fourth term in that mayoral role in spite of having been caught on videotape smoking crack in 1990. For ten points, name this longtime mayor of Washington, D.C.", "answer": "Marion<em><b> Barry</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "British officers in India created a variant of this sport in the nineteenth century using books and bottle corks. Jaques [JAKES] of London popularized a common name for this sport whose notable players include Jan-Ove Waldner and Zhang Yining. The penhold grip is often used by players from East Asia who play this sport, considered an Olympic \u201cracket\u201d sport since its introduction in 1988 even though it is played with a paddle. For ten points, name this sport sometimes called \u201cping pong.\u201d", "answer": "<em><b> Table tennis</b></em> (accept<em><b> ping pong</b></em> until mentioned) Page 1", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This state saw more than 200 battles in the American Revolutionary War, beginning with the first Battle of Ninety Six. The largest surrender of American soldiers in the Revolutionary War took place in this state after a defeat for Benjamin Lincoln, whereas another setback in this state featured Horatio Gates\u2019s loss at Camden. The fortunes of the colonists in this state fared better near the Broad River. For ten points, name this state where Daniel Morgan was victorious at Cowpens.", "answer": "<em><b> South Carolina</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While sailing for this group, Paul Beneke was put on trial for seizing a triptych from England. This group held drittel meetings in preparation for a central \u201cmeeting ride,\u201d or Tagfahrt. This group was harassed by the Likedeelers after pushing the Victual Brothers out of Gotland. This group imposed a tax on Haakon VI and his father-in-law in the Treaty of Stralsund. Centered at Lubeck, for ten points, name this German confederation of merchant guilds.", "answer": "<em><b> Hanseatic League</b></em> (accept<em><b> Hansa</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An economic advisor to this man named Fuad Shubaki alleged that this man allocated aid money for buying weaponry. The Madrid Conference of 1991 attempted to broker a peace between this man\u2019s organization and a national government. A Mukataa in Ramallah served as the central compound of this leader after he signed a 1995 agreement with Yitzhak Rabin known as the Oslo Accord. For ten points, name this longtime chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization.", "answer": "Yasser<em><b> Arafat</b></em> (accept<em><b> Abu Ammar</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man told a graduating class to \u201cbe ashamed to die until you have won some victory for humanity\u201d while president of Antioch College. This man succeeded to John Quincy Adams\u2019s House seat and criticized Daniel Webster for his support of the Compromise of 1850. After a trip to Prussia, this man founded The Common School Journal reflecting one of his main principles that the \u201cpublic should no longer remain ignorant.\u201d For ten points, name this Massachusetts education reformer.", "answer": "Horace<em><b> Mann</b></em> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, three Black teenagers were killed by police officers in the Algiers Motel Incident. A mayor who resisted deploying the National Guard during this event stated, \u201cToday we stand amidst the ashes of our hopes.\u201d This event began when police arrested 82 people celebrating the return of Vietnam veterans at an illegal bar. Mayor Jerome Cavanagh failed to prevent this event, the bloodiest of the \u201clong, hot summer.\u201d For ten points, name this 1967 event in the largest city in Michigan.", "answer": "1967<em><b> Detroit</b></em> race<em><b> riot</b></em> (accept<em><b> 12th Street Riot</b></em>, accept<em><b> Algiers Motel</b></em> Incident before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This polarizing leader of the Social Democrats promoted women\u2019s rights, helped save nuclear power in his nation, and notably called apartheid \u201ca particularly gruesome system.\u201d This man promoted the release of the documentary They Call Us Misfits that put a spotlight on \u201cjunkie\u201d culture in Stockholm. This successor of Tage [TAG-eh] Erlander is officially thought to have been murdered by drug addict Christer Pettersson. For ten points, name this Swedish Prime Minister.", "answer": "Olof<em><b> Palme</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s father commanded US forces during the Gulf of Tonkin Incident. In the summer of 1965, this man\u2019s poetry impressed fellow UCLA cinematography student, Ray Manzarek, and they formed a band with a name inspired by Aldous Huxley\u2019s 1954 work about his psychedelic experiences. This man became one of the most influential singers and songwriters in history with number one hits such as \u201cHello, I Love You\u201d and \u201cLight My Fire.\u201d For ten points, name this man, known as the \u201cLizard King,\u201d who fronted The Doors.", "answer": "Jim<em><b> Morrison</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s explorations of Alaska were chronicled in his book The Cruise of the Corwin. This man described the Calypso Borealis flower in one of his many correspondences with Jeanne Carr. With William Colby, this man led a campaign against a dam proposed by James D. Phelan. This man is best known for founding an organization in 1892 which advocated for federal acquisition of Yosemite. For ten points, name this environmental activist who founded the Sierra Club.", "answer": "John<em><b> Muir</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This state was the site of the first successful recall of a governor in US history, targeted at Lynn Frazier in 1921. Another governor of this state, William \u201cWild Bill\u201d Langer, barricaded himself in the governor\u2019s mansion and declared this state independent after he was removed from office. In 1873, the North Pacific Railway changed this state\u2019s capital from Edwinton in a move to attract German immigrants. For ten points, name this state that may or may not have entered the Union before its neighbor in 1889.", "answer": "<em><b> North Dakota</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This author profiled a member of the Communist Party in the 1967 essay \u201cComrade Laski, C.P.U.S.A. (M.L.).\u201d This author won a 2005 Pulitzer for a book describing life after the death of her husband, John Gregory Dunne. An essay by this author is titled after a quote from Yeats\u2019s \u201cSecond Coming\u201d and describes the Summer of Love in Haight-Ashbury. For ten points, name this author of The Year of Magical Thinking and Slouching Toward Bethlehem.", "answer": "Joan<em><b> Didion</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s tenure, he and his Minister of the Interior, Wolfgang Schauble [SHOY-bleh] were implicated in the Schwarzgeldaffare. All lands east of the Oder-Neisse [NIGH-suh] line were given to Poland by this leader who was succeeded in his highest office by Gerhard Schroder. Under this man, the president of the Bundesbank allowed for a 1:1 exchange of marks between West and East Germany. For ten points, name this first chancellor of re-unified Germany.", "answer": "Helmut<em><b> Kohl</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Stephen Girard stayed to help victims of this event after Bush Hill and other medical facilities were found to have unqualified staff. Matthew Clarkson was mayor during this event, during which the Free African Society volunteered to help victims. The (+) unsanitary conditions of the central city were theorized by Benjamin Rush to have caused this event, which historians now think was initiated by Caribbean refugees. This event caused George Washington\u2019s (*) </b> cabinet to reassemble in the nearby city of Germantown. For ten points, name this 1793 epidemic that affected the \u201cCity of Brotherly Love.\u201d", "answer": "1793<em><b> yellow fever</b></em> epidemic in<em><b> Philadelphia</b></em> (accept equivalents to \u201cepidemic\u201d, do not accept \u201cpandemic\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s lawyer attempted to have him acquitted by saying he was a Prussian, to which this man exclaimed \u201cI am French and will remain French!\u201d During the French (+) retreat from Russia, this man led the rearguard and was thus called \u201cthe last Frenchman in Russia.\u201d Wellington\u2019s forces at Quatre Bras were attacked by this man who joined up with his former commander after promising to bring him to Paris (*)</b> in an iron cage. This man led an unsupported cavalry charge and failed to spike British cannons at Waterloo, sealing his fate. For ten points, name this marshal of France under Napoleon.", "answer": "Michel<em><b> Ney</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Carvings from this civilization include depictions of a shaman raising the World Tree such as in the San Martin Pajapan Monument. A common motif in this civilization was a half-man, half- (+) jaguar spirit known as the were [WAIR]-jaguar, frequently depicted on Kunz axes. One mark of rank in this civilization was the possession of jade masks. San Lorenzo and La Venta were artistic centers of this civilization whose most significant (*) </b>sculptural achievements were typically formed from basalt. For ten points, name this Mesoamerican civilization that flourished from 1500 to 400 BC, best known for their giant stone heads.", "answer": "<em><b> Olmec</b></em>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>The aggressor in this battle hoped to capitalize on the fact that its opponent\u2019s armies were occupied besieging Hasedo. In this battle, Otani Yoshitsugu\u2019s line broke after the previously neutral (+) Kobayakawa Hideaki charged. One side was forced to retreat before this battle as Gifu Castle had already fallen. More than 160 thousand samurai gathered for this battle in 1600 with more than 30 thousand losing their lives. This battle was fought between (*)</b> Toyotomi loyalists like Ishida Mitsunari and a certain future shogun. For ten points, name this battle in which Tokugawa Ieyasu finalized his hold over Japan.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Sekigahara</b></em> Page 9", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man avoided combat at Campbell\u2019s Station but was finally caught at Knoxville. This man successfully defended Fort Sanders from James Longstreet as head of the Department of the (+) Ohio, a post he held when he ordered the arrest of Clement Vallandigham. One of this man\u2019s offensives was thwarted by torrential rain leading to his replacement by (*) </b>Joseph Hooker. This man failed to seize Marye\u2019s Heights from Robert E. Lee at Fredericksburg. For ten points, name this Union general whose military career ended after a disastrous loss at The Crater.", "answer": "Ambrose<em><b> Burnside</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Features along this construct included iron-cast bell-shaped \u201ccloches\u201d along with larger\u201couvrages.\u201d This construct was panned in favor of mobility in the tract \u201cArmy of the Future\u201d but was completed during the tenure of Chief of the Army Staff (+) Maurice Gamelin. A lack of action near this structure led to the so-called Phony War, though this structure later proved to be (*)</b> ineffectual as the Wehrmacht slipped through the Ardennes Forest. For ten points, name this ineffectual French defensive line in World War Two, named for the French Minister of War.", "answer": "<em><b> Maginot Line</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>According to Appian, Hannibal once claimed that this man was the second greatest general of all time as \u201che was the first to teach the art of laying out a camp.\u201d This man defeated Antigonus Gonatas at the Battle of the (+) Aous but lost his firstborn son Ptolemy in a failed siege of Sparta. During street fighting in Argos, this man was killed after he was knocked unconscious by a (*)</b> tile thrown by an old woman. For ten points, name this Molossian king who defeated Rome at the Battles of Heraclea and Asculum after which he stated, \u201cIf we are victorious in one more battle with the Romans, we shall be utterly ruined.\u201d", "answer": "<em><b> Pyrrhus</b></em> of Epirus Page 10", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>A Canadian branch of this movement caused Vancouver\u2019s Gastown riots. This party, which took ideas from the Merry Pranksters and the Rainbow Family, urged for free clinics and pirate radio in their (+) New Nation. Members of this party tried to levitate the Pentagon in 1967. The founders of this party included Nancy Kurshan, Jerry Rubin, and Abbie and Anita Hoffman. In Chicago, this party organized the Festival of Life to protest the (*)</b> 1968 Democratic National Convention. For ten points, name this counter-culture free speech party, a youth group that nominated a pig for president.", "answer": "<em><b> Youth International Party</b></em> (accept<em><b> YIP</b></em>, accept<em><b> Yippies</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}